The egg sack.
Next morning, when the first light came into the sky, and the sparrows stirred
in the trees, when the cows rattled their chains, and the rooster crowed,
and the early automobiles went whispering along the road, Wilbur awoke
and looked for Charlotte. He saw her up overhead in a corner near the back of his pin.
She was very quiet. Her eight legs were spread wide. She seemed to have shrunk
during the night. Next to her, attached to the ceiling, Wilbur saw a curious
object. It was a sort of sack or cocoon.
It was peachcoled and looked as though it were made of cotton candy.
"Are you awake, Charlotte?" he said softly. "Yes," came the answer. "What is
that nifty little thing? Did you make it? I did indeed, replied Charlotte in a
weak voice. Is it a play thing? Play thing? I should say not. It is my egg
sack. My magnum opus?
I don't know what a magnum opus is, said Wilbur. That's Latin, explained
Charlotte. It means great work. This egg sack is my great work. The finest thing
I have ever made.
What's inside it? asked Wilbur. Eggs.
514 of them, she replied. 514, said Wilbur. You're kidding.
No, I'm not. I counted them. I got started counting, so I kept on just to
keep my mind occupied.
It's a perfectly beautiful egg sack, said Wilbur, feeling as happy as though
he had constructed it himself.
Yes, it is pretty, replied Charlotte, patting the sack with her two front
legs. Anyway, I can guarantee that it is strong. It's made out of the toughest
material I have. It's also waterproof.
The eggs are inside and will be warm and dry.
Charlotte said Wilbur dreily. Are you really going to have 514 children?
If nothing happens. Yes, she said. Of course, they won't show up till next spring.
Wilbur noticed that Charlotte's voice sounded sad.
What makes you sound so downhearted?
I should think you'd be terribly happy about this. Oh, don't pay any attention
to me, said Charlotte. I just don't have much pep anymore. I guess I feel sad
because I won't ever see my children.
What do you mean you won't see your children? Of course you will. We'll all see them.
It's going to be simply wonderful next spring in the barn cellar with 514
baby spiders running around all over the place and the geese will have a new set
of gosslings and the sheep will have their new lambs.
Maybe, said Charlotte quietly.
However, I have a feeling I'm not going to see the results of last night's efforts.
I don't feel good at all. I think I'm languishing, to tell you the truth.
Wilbur didn't understand the word languish, and he hated to bother
Charlotte by asking her to explain, but he was so worried he felt he had to ask.
What does languishing mean? It means I'm slowing up, feeling my age. I'm not
young anymore, Wilbur, but I don't want you to worry about me. This is your big day today.
Look at my web. Doesn't it show up well with the dew on it? Charlotte's web
never looked more beautiful than it looked this morning. Each strand held
dozens of bright drops of early morning dew. The light from the east struck it
and made it all plain and clear. It was a perfect piece of designing and building.
In another hour or two, a steady stream of people would pass by, admiring it and
reading it, and looking at Wilbur and marveling at the miracle. As Wilbur was
studying the web, a pair of whiskers and a sharp face appeared. Slowly, Templeton
dragged himself across the pin and threw himself down in a corner.
I'm back," he said in a husky voice.
"What a night!" The rat was swollen to twice his normal size. His stomach was
as big around as a jelly jar.
"What a night!" he repeated horarssely.
"What feasting and carousing!
A real gorge!
I must have eaten the remains of 30 lunches.
Never have I seen such leings and everything well ripened and seasoned
with the passage of time and the heat of the day. Oh, it was rich, my friends.
Rich. You ought to be ashamed of yourself, said Charlotte in disgust. It
would serve you right if you had an acute attack of indigestion.
Don't worry about my stomach, snarled Templeton. It can handle anything. And
by the way, I've got some bad news. As I came past that pig next door, the one
that calls himself Funkle, I noticed a blue tag on the front of his pen. That
means he has won for his prize. I guess you licked, Wilbur. You might as well
relax. Nobody is going to hang any metal on you.
Furthermore, I wouldn't be surprised if Zuckerman changes his mind about you.
Wait till he gets hankering for some fresh pork and smoked ham and crisp
bacon. He'll take the knife to you, my boy. Be still, Templeton, said
Charlotte. You're too stuffed and bloated to know what you're saying.
Don't pay any attention to him, Wilbur.
Wilbur tried not to think about what the rat had just said. He decided to change
the subject. Templeton said, Wilbur, if you weren't so dopey, you would have
noticed that Charlotte has made an egg sack. She is going to become a mother.
For your information, there are 514 eggs in that peachy little sack. Is that
true? Asked the rat, eyeing the sack.
suspiciously.
"Yes, it's true," sighed Charlotte.
"Congratulations," murmured Templeton. "This has been a night." He closed his eyes, pulled some
straw over himself, and dropped off into a deep sleep. "Wilbur and Charlotte were
glad to be rid of him for a while. At 9:00, Mr. Arabel's truck rolled into the
fairgrounds and came to a stop at Wilbur's pen. Everybody climbed out.
Look, cried Fern. Look at Charlotte's Web. Look what it says. The grown-ups
and the children joined hands and stood there studying the new sign. Humble,
said Mr. Zuckerman. Now, isn't that just the word for Wilbur? Everyone rejoiced
to find that the miracle of the web had been repeated.
Wilbur gazed up lovingly into their faces.
He looked very humble and very grateful.
Fern winked at Charlotte. Lurvy soon got busy. He poured a bucket of warm slops
into the trough. And while Wilbur ate his breakfast, Lurvy scratched him
gently with a smooth stick. Wait a minute, cried Avery. Look at this. He
pointed to the blue tag on Uncle's pen.
This pig has won first prize already.
The Zuckerman's in the arable stared at the tag. Mrs. Zuckerman began to cry.
Nobody said a word. They just stared at the tag. Then they stared at Uncle. Then
they stared at the tag again.
Lurvy took out an enormous handkerchief and blew his nose very loud. So loud in
fact that the noise was heard by stable boys over at the horse barn.
"Can I have some money?" asked Fern. "I want to go out on the midway." "You stay
right where you are," said her mother.
Tears came to Fern's eyes. What's everybody crying about? asked Mr.
Zuckerman. Let's get busy, Edith. Bring the buttermilk. Mrs. Zuckerman wiped her
eyes with her handkerchief. She went to the truck and came back with a gallon jar of buttermilk.
"Bath time," said Zuckerman cheerfully.
"He and Mrs. Zuckerman and Avery climbed into Wilbur's pen. Avery slowly poured
buttermilk on Wilbur's head and back, and as it trickled down his sides and
cheeks, Mr. and Mrs. Zuckerman rubbed it into his hair and skin.
Passers by stopped to watch. Pretty soon, quite a crowd had gathered. Wilbur
grew beautifully white and smooth.
The morning sun shone through his pink ears.
He isn't as big as that pig next door, remarked one bystander. But he's
cleaner. That's what I like. So do I, said another man. He's humble, too, said
a woman, reading the sign on the web.
Everybody who visited the pig pin had a good word to say about Wilbur. Everyone
admired the web. And of course, nobody noticed Charlotte.
Suddenly, a voice was heard on the loudspeaker.
Attention, please. It said, "Will Mr.
Homer Zuckerman bring his famous pig to the judges booth in front of the
grandstand? A special award will be made there in 20 minutes. Everyone is invited
to attend. Crate your pig, please, Mr.
Zuckerman and report to the judge's booth promptly.
For a moment after this announcement, the arables and the Zuckermanman's were
unable to speak or move. Then Avery picked up a handful of straw and threw
it high in the air and gave a loud yell.
The straw fluttered down like confetti into Fern's hair.
Mr. Zuckerman hugged Mrs. Zuckerman. Mr.
Arable kissed Mrs. Arable. Avery kissed Wilbur. Lurvy shook hands with
everybody. Fern hugged her mother. Avery hugged Fern. Mrs. Arable hugged Mrs.
Zuckerman.
Up overhead in the shadows of the ceiling. Charlotte crouched unseen, her
front legs encircling her egg sack. Her heart was not beating as strongly as
usual, and she felt weary and old, but she was sure at last that she had saved
Wilbur's life, and she felt peaceful and contented.
"We have no time to lose," shouted Mr.
Zuckerman. "Ly, help with the crate."
"Can I have some money?" asked Fern.
"You wait," said Mrs. Arable. "Can't you see everybody's busy? Put that empty
buttermilk jar into the truck," commanded Mr. Arable. Avery grabbed the
jar and rushed to the truck.
"Does my hair look all right?" asked Mrs. Zuckerman. "Looks fine," snapped
Mr. Zuckerman as he and Lurvy set the crate down in front of Wilbur. "You
didn't even look at my hair," said Mrs.
Zuckerman. "You're all right, Edith," said Mrs. Arable. "Just keep calm."
Templeton, asleep in the straw, heard the commotion and awoke. He didn't know
exactly what was going on, but when he saw the men shoving Wilbur into the
crate, he made up his mind to go along.
He watched his chance, and when no one was looking, he crept into the crate and
buried himself in the straw at the bottom.
"All righty, boys!" cried Mr. Zuckerman.
"Let's go!" He and Mr. Arable and Lurvy and Avery grabbed the crate and boosted
it over the side of the pen and up into the truck. Fern jumped aboard and sat on
top of the crate. She still had straw in her hair and looked very pretty and excited.
Mr. Rarable started the motor. Everyone climbed in and off they drove to the
judges booth in front of the grandstand.
As they passed the ferris wheel, Fern gazed up at it and wished she were in
the topmost car with Henry Fussy at her side.
Chapter 20. The hour of triumph.